Welcome back to module six
on single table queries.
We will once again be
using the space data set,
the planet data set, excuse me.
And we have already covered in video one
the more difficult topic for this week,
aggregate functions along with the group
by clause and then the having clause.
And the second part, we will go
through the more basic topics but I
wanted to cover the more difficult
group by having first. Here are
some of the topics that we'll cover.
We'll have the distinct clause.
We'll also use where
with equal, not equal to,
greater than or less than,
greater than or equal to.
We'll use and and or conjunctions.
And just as a heads up, and in
SQL Server runs before or. And I'll
show you an example of that. and
then you'll have some examples
on both the labs and the quizzes.
We'll use in, not in,
between, like, null.
Values we'll finally approach
in terms of is or is not.
Wildcard characters,
order by, concat, write,
trim, and featuring format,
the format function.
Let's go ahead. I'll switch over to SQL
Server, and I'll try
to cover these topics,
and most of them will be covered
in the video along with the lab,
and some of them will be reinforced
primarily through the lab. Let's
go ahead and get started. We just
have on the screen select star
from planet, so this is our very
small data set that we have. At
the top of the screen I have commented
out some of the key terms that
we'll be going through in this
video. The first one is distinct.
If I type in interest, so which
planets is Dr. Sigurd interested
in, you can see we get a list. we
have 10 rows, all 10 rows show up,
but there are times, for instance,
where the question might be,
you know, what are the various
interest possibilities? And certainly
this output gives you the
possibilities, but if I include the
keyword distinct and then interest,
you can see that it will remove
any duplicate information. So
when you want to remove duplicate
information, you can use the distinct
keyword it takes place right after
the select statement and now
looking at our order of operation
in terms of order operation you
remember back in maybe middle school
we have parentheses and then in
addition to parentheses we have
exponents we have multiplication
and then division, multiplication,
and then division,
and then hi-yah,
and then addition and subtraction.
You'll likely want to be liberal
with parentheses as that can guide
the formula since parentheses will
run first. Also, this looks like an
order of operation where multiplication
takes place before division, and
that's not true. So multiplication,
division take place from left
to right, whichever comes first,
and addition and subtraction
is also from left to right.
Now the other one are these
conjunctions in SQL Server and
in OR, and this makes the
calculus, it's not calculus, but
this makes the calculations a
little more difficult because
the logic sometimes looks like it
will provide one output and the
reality because AND runs before
OR, unless you have parentheses,
will provide another one. Let's
take a look at this particular
coding problem where we introduce
the OR and the AND conjunction.
And so in this case, we have
all of our planet information.
And if we read it from left to right, we
have where location is equal to inner.
And now think of the Earth.
So the Earth is inner.
OR interest is high.
And that is also true.
And moons are greater than one.
and so in this case it might look
like earth wouldn't show up because
we have this conjunction and moons
is greater than one and we know
that earth does not have that
however if we run this code wait a
minute you can see that earth shows
up and we look at why that shows
up here is what is actually
happening it'll run the and conjunction
first so it's first running where
interest is high and moons is
greater than one, so that is true.
No, excuse me, that is false. Interest
is high and moons greater than
one, that would be false. However,
the OR would be inner, which of
course Mercury, Venus, Earth, and
in this case the moon are all inner.
And so that's why Earth will show
up. Now the use of parentheses, you
can change that logic. For instance,
if I want the OR to run first
before the end, I can provide the
parentheses and now it's going to say
where location is equal to inner
that's true for earth interest is
equal to high that's truth for earth
so these are true however we get to
the and moon's greater than one and
so by running it in a little bit
different order because of the
parentheses and now earth is removed
from this and also just some simple
order of operations we know that
multiplication takes place before
addition subtraction and so in this
particular case you could think three
plus two right five times 4, 20.
However, if we run this code, you
can see that it's going to take 4
times 3, 12, and then add the 2,
which would give you 14. Alright, now
let's take a look at three ways we
can manipulate the WHERE clause.
If I want to see all planets
where moons is equal to one or 62.
This is a common error on the
exam. If I run this code it looks
like it makes sense where moons
equal to one or 62 but if I run this
we get the error message and it's
indicating that for each value,
we need to include the column that
we're interested in evaluating.
So SQL doesn't make the assumption,
even in the current year,
SQL doesn't make the assumption
without having the column first.
So in this case, we would have to
say where moons is equal to 62.
And in this case, the
conjunction or would allow
for either. So we have moons
of one and moons of 62.
Now, if you wanted to do this five
or six times, that could be a bit
cumbersome. And so we have a couple
of new options that we'll also
include on the lab. We have in and
not in and then between conjunction.
And so let me just copy this
and I'll show you the other two.
Any three, any of these three
are great. Best practice
is just what your
preference is. But in this
case, you could indicate
where moons and then use in.
And then within in, you could
indicate the numbers. And so to be
exactly the same as we had before
you could put in 62 and you could put
one here and it would still work
but typically this is used for
multiple and so if i run this code
we get the same answer there are some
questions on the exam that will
indicate are these code or are they
equivalent are these equivalent
outputs and in this case the answer
for this would be yes if you ran
both of them the output would be
exactly the same now the other
one it doesn't fit necessarily for
this one but you also have the
between clause and this would be where
you want to include a range that
is consecutive and so we could do
the 1 and 62 here but we could do
between 1 and 62 and if we put this
code in it is a different response
but this would give us anything
between 1 and 62 and one of the
bigger questions when you're taking
the exam and you see something
like this the question would be, is
the between clause inclusive? And
you can clearly see that the answer
is yes, it is inclusive. We have
a one here and we also have a 62.
The next topic we'll cover
includes wildcard characters
along with the like that
you see on the screen.
I'm not the best at spelling on the
planet, but let's say I was really
bad. So in this case, I'd like to
see everything related to pluto and
so in this particular case you could
indicate where name is equal to and
i just don't remember how to spell
it and remember sequel is not case
sensitive puto so we think puto might
work but no we didn't get it and
yeah we know that there's something
there and so if you're not exactly
sure the spelling you can use the
wildcard character and that includes
like we'll replace the equality
symbol with like and then you also
have available to you the percent which
represents any number of characters
and also the underscore which
simply represents one unspecified
character so for instance if I knew
that it was Hawaii state abbreviation
but I can't remember the second you
could use the underscore for one
unspecified character but most of the
time you'll use the percentage and
in this case how this would work is
I know I'm going to use a wild card
so I'll put in a like and then I
know with like I need a percent or
an underscore so here if I just
remember it starts with a P I could put
this information in and run it and
it indicates Pluto and you could
also start with I don't remember what
Pluto starts with so you could go
I'm not really sure what it is but
I do know that it ends in an O and
you could put that information in and
even further I just know there's a
U in here which you probably wouldn't
do but you could you could say
is there just a U in there so anywhere
in here there's some kind of U
which will bring up a few but it
also brings up Pluto so these are the
wild card characters with like and
also the percent and the underscore.
All right let's take one of
our first look at null values.
We've already discussed,
just as a review,
if I indicate select count star
from planet and I run this code you
can see that there's ten columns.
Now if I go back and I
look at this column called
distance from the sun, you
can see we have a null value.
If I include that column in
our equation, you can see
it goes from 10 to 9. So that's
potentially one problematic
issue with the null value.
Now let's go back here
and we're going to say
select distance from the sun
in fact let's just go
back to showing everything
here so select everything from the planet
and for my predicate logic by
where clause I kind of want to
isolate this null value so we know
the distance from the sun has a
null value so I could indicate
and that refers to the moon so
I could indicate where distance
from the sun is equal to null kind
of thinking about this and I
get it nothing and sometimes the
code will say how many rows do
you expect to show up on an exam
because if I ask you will this
cause an error message in this
case it doesn't cause an error
message but nothing shows up now
I could think oh that's right
anytime we have a character value
we're going to include a
single quote around it and that
doesn't work either and so in
this particular case because it's
a null value it gets its very
own is null and in that case
it does pull up the planet
or I could say I just
don't want to see anything
that's not null value
and in that case we
expect everything to show
up except for in this in
this instance the moon
And the issue with the null
value is it's not a value, so it
doesn't really make sense to say
equal to null. So instead it has
its very own reserved word, is
or is not. So if I'm making a
flashcard again or studying for the
exam with the exam review sheet,
I would definitely associate is
or is not with the null values.
All right, let's now take a
look at the order by clause.
and in this case I show you what we
won't accept if you put in mass and name
and that's fine let's just leave
it at this from the planet in this
case you can see that it's there's
really no specified order and according
to relational algebra there is no
specified order 2 times 3 is the
same as 3 times two so by definition
the order shouldn't matter if you
need it to matter you can use an
order by we'll discuss later in the
semester how this slows down the
code when we talk about query tuning
but in this case we could order by so for
instance in fact let's
let's switch this around
how do we switch the
column order around so
we put name and mass we
have this information
and we run it and now if
we want to order by order
space by in this case if we want to
order by the the name of the planet
we have we can put in just the name
and by default the name will be
ASC like the analytical solution
center or you can put in DESC
to go from Z to A so 1 to 100 A
to Z would be the default, or I
could put ASC here either way. If
I wanted to go from Z to A, I can
put in this information. Now,
if there happens to be a tie, I
could separate this. So if we had
two that were exactly the same,
I don't think we have it in here,
but I could separate it. And
if there is a tie, we could then
order by mass or something that
doesn't show up here, any column
that we could order by. What we
don't accept, and you can read
in Ben Ghosn in a lot of detail,
is we don't accept pointers in
3330. So you could say order by,
and it looks cool, order
by one, which would
refer to name here, and
it does look kind of cool.
But in this case, Ben Ghosn
describes why this is just not best
practice. For instance, if
you change, add a column, move
something around, it's really
easy to forget about this. So it
doesn't look quite as cool, but
it's just more reliable if you
just type the columns out rather
than pointers. So just make
sure in this class that you refer
to order by columns by name.
And then let's look at a
couple of other options.
Before I forget, everything
we've done in the where
clause, so if we say
where name, for instance,
is equal to earth, just as a
reminder, any time we use character
values, we include a quote, a single
quote around it. If we're using
numeric values to analyze, so if
I put in mass is equal to, in this
case you wouldn't include a quote
around it, so 5.970, which is
getting pretty specific, but we
could do greater than or less than.
And so just as a reminder, if
it's character date or no quotes.
Okay, just a few more for today.
The next one would be concat, and I
don't necessarily have a great one
for here. Later we'll do concatenate,
put together your first and last name,
for instance, but this will still
work for for example purposes and
in this case if I have two columns
and I want to merge them into one
column I can use the concat function
so in this case I can concat name
and mass and the cat can cat just
smushes things together, if you
spell it right, and there we have the
tables concatenated. Now because
it creates one column, you would
need an alias as, we'll just call
it combined, so you would need that
alias, and if you're following along,
and you're certainly welcome to
pause the screen if moving a little
bit too quickly and here we can
also we can see on this on the backside
of mercury we look like we have
some spaces there and this looks
like it must be a char data type
not of our char and so what I can
do is I can go just directly to name
and put in an R trim and that will
eliminate those lagging spaces.
But then it kind of
introduces one more problem.
So now you can see that it's
smushed together. So I can go in and
include a literal value. In this
case, I could put in a single quote.
And by putting that single quote
in, I can at least put a space
here or something else. So as a
reminder, I can use literal values,
and I can also use column values.
Okay, the last one, I think
for today, then we'll look back
at the slice to see what I missed.
Let's just, oh, there it is, select star.
Let's look at select star from planet.
And you can see on most
of these, this one here,
it has, it looks like
three decimal places.
You can format, you can
format your code. So in
this case, I could indicate
select and then format.
This is a function and it has a couple
of arguments. The first is, what
do I want to format? So in this
case, I'm going to format mass, the
mass column, and then if you use n,
n alone, actually let's use n alone,
would change it to two
decimal places. So the default
is just two decimal places.
So you can see we have the
three decimal places here,
and if I run this column, you
can see that it drops down
to the two decimal place.
Now, if you want to put another
digit here, for instance, one decimal
place, we would drop this from two
decimal down to one decimal place.
and so now we have the decimal.
So n indicates how many decimal.
There's a lot of different options
for formatting. The only two I'll
describe here is n, and then a
value for how many decimal places.
So clearly if we put something
like n5, we get our five decimal
places. And the most common one is
probably c, because your business
major is c for currency, and so
this would put a dollar sign and
drop it down to two decimal places.
Let's go ahead and check the
slides out to see that we've
covered all the topics for today. I
think we've covered most of it.
These slides are uploaded for you.
The exam is set up first on
the lectures, so the class
slides would be probably
the number one resource.
Number two, and they do go hand
in hand, would be the labs.
And number three resource would
be the animations. As you know,
about 40% of the questions come
directly from the animation video,
and then other supplements. You
could use AI, the reading, the
been gone book to round out your
learning, but that's kind of the
order that the order of operation
order of what the exam would be.
So this goes through the order
of operation, the and and the or.
Here's an example of the in
function as a reminder where planet
ID in, planet ID in 1, 3, five
six and seven in order to do this
with typical coding you would
have to say where planet id equal
to one or planet id equal to
three or planet id equal to five
and so you can see where the the
in clause is uh is helpful the
between when you have contiguous
numbers between one and five
that works well and it's just
as a reminder that speak that's
inclusive uh the null values you
associate is null or is not null.
The wild card characters, you
would always associate like along
with either percent underscore or
some combination of both of those.
When you're sorting by
results, just as a reminder,
you'll only have one
order by forever and ever
separated by commas if you
have more than one column.
ASC for ascending and DESC, excuse
me, for descending. And then
let's just take a look at the
difference between physical and logical
SQL. So physical SQL we write
so far select from where group
by having order by we'll get to
offset fetch later but it's a
derivative of order by and then
the way the computer reads it would
be from is read first where group
by having and then select as you
can see is the second to last.
So if you create an alias in the
select statement, so select
something as combined columns, the
only place you can refer to those
would be in the order by clause.
And if you formatted something in
the select statement and gave it
an alias, you can't refer to it in
the order by either because once
you format something, it becomes
what's called an ASCII value, similar
to how you want the T to be in a
certain place on your keyboard.
there's some standards but because
you have for instance a dollar
sign and some additional decimos
it's no longer just a normal value
so if you refer to in the order
by you wouldn't refer to the alias
you just refer to the column itself
so that you don't have incorrect
data and if you try it and you
find the error then you'll you'll
know why that error takes place and
the whole idea of SQL Server was
to make it more conversational
language. If I said, for instance,
would you please get the book
from my office, that would make
sense. Would you please get
the book from my office? What
you wouldn't say is how SQL
actually reads it. You wouldn't say,
from the office, get my book,
right? So the whole idea of
this change, whether it's good
or bad, that's the reason for
it, is they wanted to make it
a more conversational language.
So that concludes the part
two of single table queries.
Best of luck on your lab,
and we will see you in a week
on introducing multiple
tables with joins. Take care.